Rue des Cigales, 13, L-1336, Luxembourg

http://tomer.libal.info

Summary

- I am a researcher, instructor and software engineer with extensive experience both in the industry and the academy.
 My academic specialization is in higher-order unification, proof certification, formal verification and theorem proving with emphasize on legal reasoning. I have experience in teaching of university level courses and have held a management position as a lead developer in a successful technology company.
- Research Topics: Automated Deduction, Proof Transformation, Legal Informatics and Formal Verification
- Teaching: Computer and Data Sciences

Experience

University of Luxembourg

Belval, Luxembourg

Researcher

- Teaching courses in the BiCS program

- A visiting researcher during Jan. 2021 - Apr. 2021

Jan. 2020 – Present

The American University of Paris

Assistant Professor for Computer Science

Paris, France Sep. 2017 – Present

- Lecturer during the academic year 2016-2017

- Teaching courses on data mining, web development, software engineering, programming and other topics

Prosecco Team - Microsoft Research - Inria Joint Center

Paris, France

Research Engineer

Jan. 2017 - Jul. 2017

- Ocaml and F* developer in the F* project

Parsifal Team - École Polytechnique/Inria

Palaiseau, France

Researcher

Researcher

Jan. 2015 - Dec. 2016

- $-\,$ Research on proof certification and unification on ERC advanced grant <code>ProofCert</code>
- Reference: Dale Miller, head of the group

École Polytechnique

Palaiseau, France

Teaching Assistant

Mar. $2015 - Aug. \ 2016$

- Teaching assistant to courses in the Master degree program
- $\,-\,$ Supervision of student projects and in terns

Microsoft Research - Inria Joint Center

Palaiseau, France Oct. 2012 – Dec. 2014

Research on theorem provers and proof assistants for the TLA+ proof language

- Modeling and verifying real time systems using the TLA Proof Assistant and Model Checker
- Reference: Leslie Lamport, head of the group

Theory and Logic Group - Vienna University of Technology

Vienna, Austria

Project Assistant

Nov. 2008 - Sep. 2012

- Researching algorithms for higher-order unification and resolution
- C, C++ and Scala developer in the Generic Architecture for Proofs project
- Reference: Alexander Leitsch, head of the group

Quigo Technologies

Tel Aviv, Israel and New York, USA

 $Sep\ 2001$ – $Jan\ 2006$

 $Programming\ Team\ Lead$

- In charge of a Big Data team developing search marketing solutions
- In charge of all the company database integration development, HTTP server side development, software deployment and continuous integration
- The company was merged¹ into AOL

Various Companies

Jerusalem, Israel

1998 - 2001

Java Programmer

- $-\,$ Surfnotes and Vertical Net Solutions
- $-\,$ Was employed as an OOP consultant to a formal text book used by computer students in Israel

¹http://techcrunch.com/2007/11/07/aol-buys-quigo-confirmed/

Education

Vienna University of Technology

Ph.D. in Computer Sciences
- Ph.D. Thesis - Unification in Higher-order Resolution

Vienna University of Technology

M.Sc in Computer Sciences
- Master Thesis: Cut Elimination in Inductive Proofs of Weakly Quantified Theorems

The Hebrew University

Vienna, Austria
2006 - 2008
2006 - 2008

Jerusalem, Israel

1998 - 2001

Academic Activities and Awards

B.Sc in Computer Sciences

- I am the principal investigator of the FNR ProofOfConcept icomplai project (€199.100, 5/21-4/23)
- I am the principal investigator of the FNR PathFinder PaCT project (€22k, 4/20-9/20)
- My paper "NAI Towards Transparent and Usable Semi-Automated Legal Analysis" has won the best paper award in IRIS 2020
- Was awarded the Erasmus Mundus scholarship for the European MSc programme Computational Logic for the academic years 2006-2007 and 2007-2008
- Reviewer for JAR, Organon F, Axioms, CADE, FSCD and various workshops, AEC member of POPL 2017 and PC member of Tableaux 2019, PxTP 2017, PAAR 2020, IJCAI 2020, CADE 2021 and EXTRAAMAS 2021
- A reviewer for Mathematical Reviews of the American Mathematical Society (since 1/20)
- Invited talks in the ReMeP '19 conference, EMCL workshop and in dedicated seminars in Universite Paris Diderot, Universite Savoie-Mont Blanc, ENS Cachan and others
- Thesis supervision of one master and three bachelor students

Software

- The original creator and a lead developer of the GAPT framework. ∼100k lines of Scala code.
- The original creator and a lead developer of the NAI normative reasoner. $\sim \! 15 \mathrm{k}$ lines of JavaScript code.
- A lead developer of the Checkers proof checker. ~2k lines of Prolog code and shell scripts.
- A lead developer of Quigo's FeedPoint tool and a major contributor to Quigo's AdSonar tool. ∼150k lines of Java code.
- A major contributor to the TLA+ Proof System. \sim 37k lines of OCaml code.
- A minor contributor to the F^* language. $\sim 300 k$ lines of OCaml, F# and F^* code.
- A minor contributor to the Leo III theorem prover. ~30k lines of Scala code.
- Various tools for education and research in different programming languages.

Teaching

- Discrete Math 1. FA20.
- Information Management 2. SP20.
- Intro to Web Authoring. FA16, FA17, FA18, SP19, FA19, SP21.
- Database Applications. FA16, FA18, SP21.
- Software Engineering. FA16, SP18.
- Advanced Java Programming. SP17, SP18, SP19, SP21.
- Data Science. FA17, SP19.
- Web Applications. FA17, FA19.
- The Symbolic Mind. FA18, FA19.
- Les principes des langages de programmation. SP15, SP16. (TA)
- Computational Logic: Artificial Intelligence in Mathematical Reasoning. FA15. (TA)

Publications

- [1] T. Libal, M. Pascucci, L. van der Torre and D. Gabbay, "A bimodal simulation of defeasibility in the normative domain," 2020. FCR.
- [2] T. Libal, "Towards Automated GDPR Compliance Checking," 2020. TAILOR.
- [3] T. Libal, "A Meta-level Annotation Language for Legal Texts," 2020. CLAR.
- [4] T. Libal and A. Steen, "Towards an Executable Methodology for the Formalization of Legal Texts," 2020. CLAR.
- [5] T. Libal and T. Novotna, "Towards Automating Inconsistency Checking of Legal Texts," 2020. IRIS.
- [6] T. Libal and A. Steen, "NAI Towards Transparent and Usable Semi-Automated Legal Analysis," 2020. IRIS (best paper).
- [7] T. Libal and A. Steen, "The NAI Suite Drafting and Reasoning over Legal Texts," 2019. JURIX.
- [8] T. Libal and M. Pascucci, "Automated Reasoning in Normative Detachment Structures with Ideal Conditions," 2019. ICAIL.
- [9] T. Libal and A. Steen, "NAI The Normative Reasoner," 2019. ICAIL.
- [10] T. Libal and M. Volpe, "A general proof certification framework for modal logic," 2019. J. of MSCS.
- [11] T. Libal, "A Simple Semi-automated Proof Assistant for First-order Modal Logics," 2018. ARQNL.
- [12] T. Libal, "Implementing a Proof Assistant using Focusing and Logic Programming," 2018. UITP.
- [13] T. Libal, X. Steele "Determinism in the Certification of UNSAT Proofs," 2017. PxTP.
- [14] T. Libal and A. Steen, "Towards a substitution tree based index for higher-order resolution theorem provers," 2016. PAAR.
- [15] T. Libal and M. Volpe, "Certification of prefixed tableau proofs for modal logic," 2016. GandALF.
- [16] S. Azaiez, D. Doligez, M. Lemerre, T. Libal and S. Merz, "Proving Determinacy of the PharOS Real-Time Operating System," 2016. ABZ.
- [17] T. Libal and D. Miller, "Functions-as-constructors higher-order unification," 2016. FSCD.
- [18] T. Libal, "Regular patterns in second-order unification," 2015. CADE.
- [19] R. Blanco, T. Libal and D. Miller, "Defining the meaning of TPTP formatted proofs," 2015. IWIL.
- [20] Z. Chihani, T. Libal, and G. Reis, "The proof certifier checkers," 2015. TABLEAUX.
- [21] D. Doligez, J. Kriener, L. Lamport, T. Libal, and S. Merz, "Coalescing: Syntactic abstraction for reasoning in first-order modal logics," 2015. ARQNL.
- [22] T. Libal, M. Riener and M. Rukhaia, "Advanced Proof Viewing in ProofTool," 2014. UITP.
- [23] T. Libal, "Bounded higher-order unification using regular terms," 2014. EPiC Series in Computing.
- [24] S. Hetzl, T. Libal, M. Riener, and M. Rukhaia, "Understanding resolution proofs through herbrand's theorem," 2013. TABLEAUX.
- [25] C. Dunchev, A. Leitsch, T. Libal, M. Riener, M. Rukhaia, D. Weller and B. Woltzenlogel-Paleo, "PROOFTOOL: a GUI for the GAPT Framework," 2013. UITP.
- [26] C. Dunchev, A. Leitsch, T. Libal, M. Riener, M. Rukhaia, D. Weller and B. Woltzenlogel-Paleo, "System feature description: Importing refutations into the gapt," 2012. PxTP.
- [27] C. Dunchev, A. Leitsch, T. Libal, D. Weller and B. Woltzenlogel-Paleo, "System Description: The Proof Transformation System CERES," 2010. IJCAR.